本节我们看看另外一种
In this segment we're gonna look at
another method to achieve chosen plain
获取选择明文攻击安全的方法，
比CBC要更好一些，叫做随机计数器模式
text security that's actually superior to
CBC. And this method is called randomized
与CBC不同，随机计数器模式使用安全的PRF
counter mode. Unlike CBC. Randomized
counter mode uses a secure PRF. It doesn't
它不使用分组密码，对于计数器模式而言
使用PRF是足够的
need a block cypher. It's enough for
counter mode to just use a PRF because
因为我们从不求这个函数F的逆
我们设F为一个安全的PRF
we're never going to be inverting this
function F. So we're going to let F be the
它定义在N字节的分组上。如果我们使用AES，N将是128
secure PRF and it acts on N byte blocks.
Again if we use AES, N will be 128. And
加密算法以计数器模式工作，开始时
the way the encryption algorithm works in
counter mode is it starts off by choosing
选择一个随机IV，对于AES是128位的随机IV
a random IV, that's 128 bits random IV in
the case of AES, and the essentially we
然后我们开始计数。从这个随机IV开始
大家注意第一个加密是IV的
start counting. From this random IV, so
you notice the first encryption is of IV
然后是IV+1，一直到IV+L。所以我们生成了这个
随机密码本。我们将结果和明文信息异或
then IV+1 up to IV+L. So we generate this
random pad. We XOR the result with the
得到密文。通常，大家注意
message, and that gives us the cipher
text. And, as usual, you notice that the
这里的IV被包含在密文里了，这样一来
IV here is included along with the cipher
text. So that, in fact, the cipher text is
事实上密文要比明文稍微长一点
a little longer than the original plain
text. And the point, of course, is that,
当然加密算法对每条明文信息都选择一个新的IV
encryption algorithm chooses a new IV for
every message. And so even if I encrypt
因此即使我加密同样的明文信息两次
我也会得到不同的两个密文
the same message twice, I'm gonna get
different resulting cipher texts. One
需要注意一点，这个模式是完全可并行的
这点与CBC不像
thing to notice that this mode is
completely parallelizable, unlike CBC. CBC
CBC是串行的。换句话说，在加密第5个分组前
was sequential. In other words, you
couldn't encrypt block #5 until you've
你必须先加密第1到第4个分组
这样硬件公司让多个AES引擎
encrypted blocks #1 to 4, so
hardware companies who might have multiple
并行工作，却并不适用于使用CBC加密
AES engines working in parallel cannot
actually use those AES engines when using
因为CBC先天就是串行的。所以即使
你可能有两个、三个或四个AES引擎
CBC because CBCs inherently sequential. So
even though you might have two or three of
用CBC时你可能只能使用一个AES引擎
four AES engines, you could only use one
of them when doing CBC encryption. With
用计数器模式时，一切都是完全可并行的
如果你有三个AES加密引擎
counter mode, everything is completely
parallelizable. If you have three AES engines
工作速度会是原来的三倍
这就是计数器模式优美的地方
encryption basically will work three times
as fast. So that's the beauty of counter
计数器模式还有一种基于新鲜值的计数器模式
mode. And counter mode also has a
corresponding nonce based counter mode.
IV不是真随机的，而是一个新鲜值
Where the IV is not truly random, but
rather, is just a nonce which could
新鲜值可以是计数器。实现基于新鲜值的计数器模式
be a counter. And the way you would
implement nonce based counter mode, is you
你可以取AES的128位分组
然后把它分成两部分
would take the 128 bits block that used in
AES. And then you would split it in two.
使用左边64位作为新鲜值
这样计数器的范围就是
You would use the left 64 bits as the
nonce, so the counter say would count from
从0到2的64次方。这是新鲜值部分
zero to 2 to the 64. And then, that will
be the nonce part of it. And then once you
一旦你指定了新鲜值，低64位用于在
specify the nonce, the lower order, 64
bits, would be doing the counting inside
计数器加密模式的内部计数
好，新鲜值在左
of the counter modes encryption. Okay, so
nonce goes on the left, and the
计数器加密模式的计数器在右
counter mode encryption counter goes on
the right. And it's perfectly fine if this
如果这个新鲜值不可预测，那也很好
唯一的限制是你最多可以
nonce is unpredictable. The only
restriction is that you encrypt at most
加密2的64次方个分组，使用一个新鲜值
危险之处在于
2 to the 64 blocks using one particular
nonce. The danger is that you don't
我们不想让计数器重置到0
如果是那样的话，你会有两个分组
want this counter to reset to zero so
that, then, you will have two blocks. Say,
这个和这个，它们使用同一密钥和一次性密码本加密的
this guy, this guy, and this guy that are
encrypted using the same one time pad.
这个和这个。我们快速地看这个安全性定理
Namely this one and this one. So let's
quickly state the security theorem for a
关于随机计数器模式的。现在大家应该对
这类定理很习惯了
randomized counter mode. By now you should
be used to these kind of theorems.
我们有一个安全的PRF，最后我们得到一个加密机制
Basically we are given a secure PRF. What
we end up with is an encryption scheme.
我们称之为E_CTR，CTR是计数器模式的意思
E_CTR在选择明文攻击下是语义安全的
We'll call it E sub CTR, E sub counter
mode, which is semantically secure under a
他加密L个分组长的明文信息
chosen plain text attack. It encrypts
messages that are L blocks long, and
产生L+1个分组的密文，因为IV必须被
produces cipher text that are L+1 blocks
long because the IV has to be included in
包含在密文中。这是针对随机计数器模式的
the cipher text. This is for randomized
counter mode. And the error bounds
这是误差范围。基本上和CBC的误差范围一样
are stated over here. It's basically the
same bounds as in the case of CBC
通常，我们能证明这一项是可忽略的
因为PRF F是安全的
encryption. As usual, we argue that this
term is negligible because the PRF F is
我们可以推出这一项是可忽略的
secure and we would like to deduce from
that, that this term is negligible so that
这样E_CTR是安全的。不幸的是，我们有这里的误差项
E_CTR is secure. Unfortunately we have this
error term here and so we have to make
我们必须确保这一误差项也必须是可忽略的
这样我们必须确保(q^2)L小于分组大小
sure this error term is negligible. And
for that we have to make sure Q squared L
记住q是使用一个密钥加密的明文数
is less than the size of a block. And
remember, Q is the number of messages
L是这些明文的最大长度
encrypted under a particular key. And L is
the maximum length of those messages. Now
有趣的是，在CBC下，我们有q^2L^2小于|X|
interestingly in the case of CBC we have Q
squared L squared has to be less than x.
而我们的计数器模式要好一些，换句话说
Which is actually worse than we have for
counter modes. In other words, counter
计数器模式实际上可以比CBC加密更多的分组
modes can actually be used for more
blocks than CBC could. Let's see a quick
让我们看一个简单例子。这里是
计数器模式的误差项
example of that. So here is, again, the
error term for counter mode, and remember
记住q是用同一密钥加密的明文数
L是明文分组数
Q is again the number of messages
encrypted with a key, and L is the length
和之前CBC的情况一样，假设我们希望
of those messages. And as before, just as
in the case of CBC, suppose we want the
攻击者的优势最多为1除以2的32次方
adversary's advantage to be at most, one
over 2 to the 32. That basically requires
要求q^2 L除以|X|小于1除以2的32次方
that this Q-squared, L over X be less than
1 over 2 to the 32. So for AES what
对于AES，如果带入|X|=2^128
happens is, if you plug in the values X is
2 to 128, 128 bit blocks. So Q times
那么q乘以L的平方根应当小于2的48次方
square root of L should be less than 2
to the 48. This is basically the bound you
这是带入2的128次方后得到的误差上界
get from plugging in 2 to the 128 into
this bound here. And as a result, you can
因此，大家可以看到，如果加密的每条明文
都是2的32次方个分组
see if you're encrypting messages that are
each, 2 to the 32 blocks. Then after 2
那么在加密了2的32次方个这样的明文后
就必须更换密钥了
to the 32 such messages you have to
replace your secret key, otherwise
否则随机计数器模式就不再是CPA安全的了
这意味着我们可以加密
randomized counter mode is no longer CPA
secure. So this means we could encrypt a
一共2的64次方个AES分组，使用一个密钥
total of 2 to the 64 AES blocks using a
single secret key. Remember, for CBC the
记住，对于CBC来说，这个值是2的48次方个分组
所以事实上因为计数器模式
corresponding value was 2 to the 48
blocks so in fact because counter mode has
具有更好的安全参数，我们可以使用同样的密钥
a better security parameterization in fact
we can use the same key to encrypt more
使用计数器模式加密比使用CBC更多的明文
blocks with counter mode than we could
with CBC. So I wanted to do a quick
那么我想简单比较一下计数器模式和CBC
从各个方面证明
comparison of counter mode and CBC. And
argue that in every single aspect, counter
计数器模式优于CBC。这也是为什么大多数的
mode is superior to CBC. And that's
actually why most modern encryption
现代加密机制都开始转向计数器模式了，放弃CBC了
schemes actually are starting to migrate
to counter mode, and abandoned CBC. Even
即使CBC依然广为应用
那么我们来看这个比较
though CBC is still quite widely used. So
let's look at the comparison. First of
首先，记得CBC必须使用分组密码
因为如果你看解密电路
all, recall that CBC actually had to use a
block cypher because if you look at the
解密电路其实是逆向地运行分组密码
decryption circuit, the decryption circuit
actually ran the block cypher in reverse.
它其实是在运用分组密码的解密功能
It was actually using the decryption
capabilities of the block cypher. Whereas
在计数器模式里，我们只使用PRF
我们从来不使用分组密码的解密功能
in counter mode, we only use a PRF. We
never ever, ever use the decryption
我们只使用正向的加密功能
capabilities of the block cypher. We only
use it in the forward direction, only
正因为这点，计数器模式更为一般
encrypt with it. Because of this, counter
mode is actually more general and you can
你能使用像Salsa一样的原型，例如Salsa20
如果你还记得，它是PRF
use primitives like Salsa, for example,
Salsa20, if you remember, as a PRF.
但不是PRP。所以计数器模式可以用Salsa
但CBC不能用。本质上
But is not a PRP. So counter mode can
Salsa but CBC cannot. And in essence,
计数器模式要比CBC更为一般化
我们说了，计数器模式
counter mode is more general than CBC.
Counter mode, as we said, is actually
是可并行的，而CBC是一个非常串行化的过程
我们说了计数器模式更安全一些
parallel, whereas CBC is a very sequential
process. We said that counter mode is more
计数器模式的安全上界、误差项比CBC好
secure. The security bounds, the error
terms are better for counter mode than
因此，在计数器模式中，你可以
使用一个密钥去加密比CBC
they are for CBC. And as a result, you can
use a key to encrypt more blocks in
更多的明文分组。另外一点是，记得在CBC中
counter mode than you could with CBC. The
other issue is, remember in CBC we talked
我们讨论过假的补齐分组，如果你的明文信息
长度正好是分组长度的倍数的话
about the dummy padding block. If you had
a message that's a multiple of the block
在CBC中我们说过，这时是必须加一个假的补齐分组的
而在计数器模式下
length. In CBC we said that we had to add
a dummy block whereas in counter mode this
这不是必须的。尽管我曾想提到
wasn't necessary. Although, I did want
to mention that there is a variation of
有一个CBC变种叫做CBC密文偷窃
可以用来避免产生假的分组
CBC called CBC with ciphertext stealing, that
actually avoids the dummy block issue. So
所以对于标准的CBC，我们其实需要一个假的分组
for standardized CBC, we actually need a
dummy block. But in fact there is a
但事实上有一种对CBC的修改可以不需要
这么一个假的分组，就像计数器模式一样
modification to CBC that doesn't need a
dummy block. Just like counter mode.
最后，假设大家加密一个一字节的信息流
Finally, suppose you're encrypting just a
stream of one byte messages, and using
使用隐藏的新鲜值进行新鲜值加密
nonce encryption with an implicit
nonce. So, the nonce is not
因此新鲜值不包含在密文里。这种情况下
每个一字节的信息都必须
included in the cipher text. In this case,
every single one byte message would have
被扩展成16字节的分组，然后才能加密
to be expanded into a sixteen byte block
and then encrypted, and the result would
结果是16字节分组。所有如果你有比如
100个一字节的信息组成的流
be a sixteen byte block. So if you have,
like, a stream of 100 one byte messages,
每一个信息都被扩成16字节的分组
each one separately would have to become a
sixteen byte block. And you'll end up
你最终得到的是一连串16字节的密文流
密文长度被扩张成了原来的16倍
with a stream of 16 byte cipher texts. So
you get a 16x expansion on the length of
与原来的密文相比。而在计数器模式里
the cipher text, compared to the length of
the plain text. In counter mode, of
这当然不是问题。你可以加密一字节信息
course, this is not a problem. You would
just encrypt each one byte message by
通过与计数器模式产生的流的第一个字节进行异或
XORing with the first bytes of the stream
that's generated in the counter mode. So
所以每个密文都将是一个字节的，和明文一样
every cipher text would just be one byte,
just like the corresponding plain text.
使用计数器模式，无需扩张
那么大家看到，本质上
And so no expansion at all, using counter
mode. So you see that essentially, every
从各个方面讲，计数器模式都完爆CBC
single aspect counter mode dominates CBC.
And that's why it's actually the
这就是为什么现在我们推荐计数器模式。好
关于选择明文攻击安全的讨论先告一段落
recommended mode to be using today. Okay,
so this concludes our discussion of chosen
我想简单总结一下
plaintext security. I wanted to just
quickly summarize and remind you that
提醒大家我们将使用分组密码的
这些PRP和PRF的抽象概念
we're going to be using these PRP and PRF
abstractions of block ciphers.
这实际上是使用分组密码的正确方式
This is actually the correct way of
thinking of block ciphers and so we'll
我们总是把它们当成伪随机置换
always think of them as either
pseudorandom permutations or pseudorandom
或伪随机函数。然后我想再提醒一下大家
目前我们有了两种安全的观念
functions. And then I wanted to remind you
again that, so far, we saw two notions of
两个都是只针对窃听攻击提供的安全性
security. Both only provide security
against eavesdropping. They don't provide
它们不提供对篡改密文的安全性
security against tampering with the cipher
text. One was used when the key is only
一个只能用于加密单个密文
另一个只能用于密钥被用来加密
used to encrypt a single message. The
other one was used when the key was used
多个明文信息时。如我们所说
因为两个安全都不是
to encrypt multiple messages. And as we
said, because neither one is designed to
为密文篡改而设计的，都不提供数据完整性保护
defend against tampering, neither one
provides data integrity. And we're going
我们将会看到，这是一个实实在在的问题
因此，事实上在下一节
to see this as a real problem. And as a
result, in fact, I'm going to say in the
我将谈到，这些模式其实永远都不能被使用了
next segment that these modes actually
should never, ever be used. You should
大家必须加上完整性机制后，才能使用它们
only be using these modes in addition to
an integrity mechanism, which is our next
完整性机制是我们的下一话题
目前我们看了使用一个密钥一次
topic. Okay, so, so far we've seen
basically for using a, the key once, you
大家可以使用流密码或确定的计数器模式
can use stream ciphers or you can use
deterministic counter mode. If you're
如果大家要使用同一密钥多次，可以使用
随机CBC或随机计数器模式
gonna use the key many times you could use
randomize CBC or randomize counter mode
我们将讨论如何提供完整性和私密性
and we're gonna talk about how to provide
integrity and confidentiality. Once we
一旦讲了完整性，即下一章的内容
cover the topic of integrity, which is our
next module.
【伊卡酱 译注】